ERDEM ÜNAL

 $+49 (1520) 325 4846 \diamond Berlin, Germany$

gMail o Personal Website o LinkedIn o GitHub o Google Scholar

OBJECTIVE

As a Data Engineer with 5+ years of experience in software development, I've been working in various Data Engineering, DevOPs and ML Engineering tasks like Cloud Migration, Business Data Analytics, Scheduled Data Pipelining, AI Music Information Retrieval - Tagging - Similarity, Project Management, Automated Rollback and Deployment Management, I'm looking for a full-time Data Architect / ML-Ops Engineer position where I can tackle in more challenging and rewarding tasks.

SKILLS

Essentials	Python, SQL, git, Bash, terraform, docker, gcloud (%70), aws (%20),
	az (%10), Visual Studio Code
Google Cloud Components	Artifact Registry, Bigquery, Looker, Cloud Build, Cloud Function, Cloud Run
Compute Services	Kubernetes Cluster, Virtual Machines, Google Compute Engine, Amazon
	EC2, Load Balancing
Data Analytics	BigQuery, Looker, Dashboards, Stackdriver, Cloud Logging and Monitoring
Data Storage (SQL, noSQL)	MySQL, PostgreSQL, Amazon S3, Google Cloud Storage, Azure Blob Storage,
	Redis, Firebase, BigQuery, Cloud SQL, Firestore, SAP BW
Data Processing	Apache Spark, Apache Airflow, Excel, Data Ingestion and Warehousing,
	ELT pipelineing, CI-CD, Dataproc, Google Workflows, Cloud Scheduler
Deep Learning	RNNs, CNNs, Generative Networks (GANs, VAEs, Flows), Autoregressive
	Models, Fairness, Pattern Recognition, Unsupervised Outlier Detection
	Google Vertex AI
Soft Skills	Responsible, Innovative, Open-Minded, Non-stop Learner, Critical Thinker

EXPERIENCE

Data Engineer

BMG - The New Music Company

Full Time, Apr 2022 - Ongoing Berlin, Germany

- ELT connection from SAP BW to BigQuery, BigQuery to Looker integration, LookML development
- ML-Ops lifecycle, end-to-end workflow, fully containerized application running on multitenancy Kubernetes cluster
- Deep Learning Research in Music Similarity, Tagging and Information Retrieval tasks targeting BMG Music Catalogue
- CI-CD pipeline using Bitbucket, Cloud Build, JIRA, Confluence
- Automated cloud operations (resource management, IAM permissions) using Terraform and GCP

Data Analyst Anvajo GmbH

Full Time, May 2021 - January 2022 Dresden, Germany

- Conducted research in unsupervised anomaly detection methods for microscopic imaging (Master's Thesis)
- Pre-processing of microscopic data for ML pipeline, CI-CD workflow, computationally efficient CNNs, variational and autoregressive generative models
- Robust detection of image samples and distributions using statistical and ML-based detectors
- Optimized inference time and cost of pretrained ML model on NVIDIA Jetson Nano
- References available upon request (Dr. Thomas Neumann)

Research Assistant DiscoRet Part Time, May 2021 - Apr 2022 Dresden, Germany

- Participated in research studies and published "Enhancing Fairness of Visual Attribute Predictors" in ACCV Conference.
- Research topics: Fairness, Robust Generative Models (VAEs, GANs, INNs), Latent Space manipulation, Hyperparameter optimization, Neural Architecture Search, AutoML
- References available upon request (Nishant Kumar) (Dmitrij Schlesinger)

Python Programmer

Part Time, Dec 2019 - May 2020

Dresden, Germany

Helmholtz-Zentrum Dresden-Rossendorf

• Designed a UNIX command line tool that queries popular AI hubs for pre-trained weights of a given architecture

• References available upon request (Dr. rer. nat. Peter Steinbach)

C++ Programmer

TU Dresden CGV

Part Time, Dec 2019 - May 2020

Dresden, Germany

• Applied ray tracing algorithms to further improve a Virtual Reality project using OpenGL and C++

• References available upon request (Prof. Dr. Stefan Gumhold)

Intern Part Time, June 2018 - Sep 2018

Fraunhofer IIS/EAS

Dresden, Germany

• Analysis of FinFET layouts and its implications to analog design

• Analysis of FinFET layouts and its implications to analog design

Saurer Schlafhorst

Intern

Part Time, June 2017 - Aug 2017

Übach-Palenberg, Germany

• Involved in project groups related to hardware designs of new products, software solutions and repair shops

EDUCATION

Master of Science: Visual Computing

2019-2021

Department of Computer Science - Dresden University of Technology - Dresden, Germany

CGPA: 2.1 – GUT (German Grade)

Thesis: Out-of-distribution Detection for Microscopic Imaging Publication: Enhancing Fairness of Visual Attribute Predictors

Topics: Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Computer Graphics, High Performance Computing, Data Visualization

Bachelor of Science: Electrical and Electronics Engineering

2015 - 2019

Department of Engineering - Bilkent University - Ankara, Turkey

CGPA: 3.19 - Honor Student (American Grade)

Final Project: LocInCampus - 2D outdoor localization system independent of GPS functioning in Bilkent University Campus borders

Topics: Telecommunications, Computational Neuroscience, Digital Signal Processing, Statistical Learning and Data Analytics, Reinforcement Learning, Computer Networks, Embedded Systems

- Bilkent IEEE Student Branch Active Member (2014-2016)

- Algorithms & Programming Course (JAVA) Grader and Tutor (2015-2017)

High School Degree

2010 - 2014

Bornova Anatolian High School - Izmir, Turkey

CGPA: 85.7/100

PUBLICATIONS

Enhancing Fairness of Visual Attribute Predictors

Authors: Tobias Hänel, Nishant Kumar, Dmitrij Schlesinger, Mengze Li, Erdem Ünal, Abouzar Eslami, Stefan

Gumhold

Publication date: 2022

Conference: Proceedings of the Asian Conference on Computer Vision

Pages: 1211-1227

PROJECTS (GITHUB)

Out-of-distribution Detection for Microscopic Imaging (2021) Master's degree final project – Thesis

Analysis and design of SOTA anomaly detection approaches suitable for microscopic data while fulfilling the requirements of the hardware. Multiple unsupervised CNN-based classifiers and deep generative models are evaluated in terms of accuracy and efficiency.

Techs: Python, TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch

Real-Time Video Segmentation (2021) Segmentation models trained on water images and then further transformed into CoreML environment and realtime mobile compatible water segmentation app is developed.

Techs: Python, PyTorch, Kaggle, ONNX, CoreML, Swift, Metal

ImageCluster (2021) Image clustering algorithm based on MPEG-7 Color Layout Descriptor using Java.

VR-Mesh View (2020) A Virtual Reality environment where you can load meshes and play with them.

Techs: C++, OpenGL, Steam VR, Visual Studio

DeepDoom (2018) A self defender algorithm for the popular gaming franchise Doom by using the essentials of reinforcement learning and Q-learning.

Techs: Python, Java, PyTorch, Kaggle, NetBeans

New York Times 5x5 Mini Crossword Puzzle Solver (2018) Machine learning project that solves the daily posted mini crossword puzzle at New York Times website based on the given clue

Techs: Java, JavaScript, HTTP5, Selenium, Eclipse, Sublime Text

Magnetic Levitation Circuit (2017) The circuit, built by using photo detectors and IR LED, suspends objects a set distance below an electromagnet

Audio Toolbox (2016) Atmel 8051 microcontroller based design that filters the given audio signal by using the principles of FIR filters

Space Shooter Game (2016) VHDL based shooting game using Basys3 FPGA board and VGA monitor.

Techs: VHDL, XILINX ISE Design Suite

Bilgiman Project (2016) Design of the backend database and website of Bilgiman Co. Ltd

Techs: C++, PHP, MySQL, HTML5, JavaScript, QT Creator, Sublime Text

BilShare (2015) Mobile based Android e-commerce application that lets students of Bilkent University sell, buy or borrow their goods and products

Techs: Java, Android, MySQL, HTML5, JavaScript, PHP, Android Studio

LANGUAGES

• English: Fluent

• German: Intermediate

• Turkish: Native

CERTIFICATES

- Received Merit Scholarship from Bilkent University (2016-2017)
- TOEFL IBT: 90/120 (2018)
- Awarded Fit (Sports) Challenge 1st Place (2018-2019)
- Bilkent Under Water Community 1* Scuba Diver (2016-2017)

INTERESTS AND HOBBIES

- Escaping European winter by working remote on the Southern Hemisphere
- Bodybuilding, calisthenics and swimming
- Development of webcrawlers, bot accounts and media content capturers
- Traditional quantitative investing and AI approach to investing